<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" version="2.0"><channel><title><![CDATA[CreatingSolutions]]></title><description><![CDATA[CreatingSolutions]]></description><link>https://www.creating-solutions.org/blog</link><generator>RSS for Node</generator><lastBuildDate>Thu, 20 Feb 2025 15:52:39 GMT</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://www.creating-solutions.org/blog-feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title><![CDATA[Winter Blues?]]></title><description><![CDATA[@graphicdepend As winter settles in, many of us feel a noticeable shift in mood. The cold, shorter days, and lack of sunlight can affect...]]></description><link>https://www.creating-solutions.org/post/winter-blues</link><guid isPermaLink="false">678190e21ae11f09c6641a28</guid><pubDate>Fri, 10 Jan 2025 21:59:05 GMT</pubDate><enclosure url="https://static.wixstatic.com/media/703483_73056e156e3a439e98a5ab543a546cc5~mv2.jpg/v1/fit/w_1000,h_960,al_c,q_80/file.png" length="0" type="image/png"/><dc:creator>Mary Rogers Kirby</dc:creator><content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><br /></p>
<figure><img src="https://static.wixstatic.com/media/703483_73056e156e3a439e98a5ab543a546cc5~mv2.jpg/v1/fit/w_1000,h_960,al_c,q_80/file.png"title="@graphicdepend"></figure>
<p><span style="color: rgb(0, 0, 0);"><span style="background-color: transparent;">As winter settles in, many of us feel a noticeable shift in mood. The cold, shorter days, and lack of sunlight can affect our emotional well-being, leading to feelings of sadness, lethargy, or even a more persistent form of depression known as Seasonal Affective Disorder (SAD). </span></span></p>
<p><span style="color: rgb(0, 0, 0);"><span style="background-color: transparent;">Here are some strategies for dealing with winter blues in a way that nurtures your mental health:</span></span></p>
<p><br /></p>
<h3><span style="color: rgb(0, 0, 0);"><span style="background-color: transparent;"><strong>1. Acknowledge the Feeling</strong></span></span></h3>
<p><span style="color: rgb(0, 0, 0);"><span style="background-color: transparent;">One of the first steps in dealing with winter blues is recognizing that what you&apos;re experiencing is valid. Seasonal changes are known to impact our mood, and many people feel the emotional shift when winter arrives. It&apos;s important to remind yourself that it&apos;s okay to feel off during this time of year, and acknowledging these feelings without judgment is an essential part of self-care.</span></span></p>
<p><br /></p>
<h3><span style="color: rgb(0, 0, 0);"><span style="background-color: transparent;"><strong>2. Maximize Natural Light</strong></span></span></h3>
<p><span style="color: rgb(0, 0, 0);"><span style="background-color: transparent;">As the days get shorter, it’s easy to find yourself deprived of the sunlight that plays a key role in regulating our mood. Sunlight stimulates the production of serotonin, a neurotransmitter that helps improve mood and focus. If possible, try to spend time outside during daylight hours. Even brief walks outside or simply sitting near a window can make a difference.</span></span></p>
<p><span style="color: rgb(0, 0, 0);"><span style="background-color: transparent;">If natural light is scarce, consider using a light therapy box. Light therapy mimics natural sunlight, helping to regulate your circadian rhythms and lift your mood.</span></span></p>
<p><br /></p>
<h3><span style="color: rgb(0, 0, 0);"><span style="background-color: transparent;"><strong>3. Prioritize Exercise</strong></span></span></h3>
<p><span style="color: rgb(0, 0, 0);"><span style="background-color: transparent;">Physical activity is a powerful tool when it comes to mental health.. Even though winter weather may make it tempting to stay indoors, try to find ways to move your body, whether that means indoor workouts, yoga, or bundling up and going for a brisk walk.</span></span></p>
<p><span style="color: rgb(0, 0, 0);"><span style="background-color: transparent;">Exercise boosts energy levels and stimulates the release of endorphins, often referred to as “feel-good” hormones. They can improve mood and reduce anxiety, which can help combat the fatigue that often accompanies the winter months.</span></span></p>
<p><br /></p>
<h3><span style="color: rgb(0, 0, 0);"><span style="background-color: transparent;"><strong>4. Maintain a Healthy Routine</strong></span></span></h3>
<p><span style="color: rgb(0, 0, 0);"><span style="background-color: transparent;">During winter, it&apos;s easy to slip into unhealthy habits, like oversleeping, eating comfort foods, or withdrawing from social interactions. Maintaining a structured daily routine can help combat this tendency. Go to bed and wake up at the same time each day, plan balanced meals, and schedule time for both work and rest.</span></span></p>
<p><span style="color: rgb(0, 0, 0);"><span style="background-color: transparent;">Creating a routine can provide structure and stability, which is especially important when external circumstances like the weather or daylight hours feel out of our control.</span></span></p>
<p><br /></p>
<h3><span style="color: rgb(0, 0, 0);"><span style="background-color: transparent;"><strong>5. Stay Connected</strong></span></span></h3>
<p><span style="color: rgb(0, 0, 0);"><span style="background-color: transparent;">Social isolation is a common challenge during the winter months, as people tend to stay indoors more and avoid social gatherings due to the cold or dark weather. However, maintaining connections with loved ones is crucial for mental health. Even if you can’t meet in person, reach out through phone calls, video chats, or text messages. Sometimes just hearing a familiar voice can provide comfort and help alleviate feelings of loneliness.</span></span></p>
<p><span style="color: rgb(0, 0, 0);"><span style="background-color: transparent;">Consider participating in winter activities that bring you joy, like cooking meals together, watching movies, or even volunteering—engaging with others can provide a sense of purpose and connection.</span></span></p>
<p><br /></p>
<h3><span style="color: rgb(0, 0, 0);"><span style="background-color: transparent;"><strong>6. Practice Mindfulness and Stress-Reduction</strong></span></span></h3>
<p><span style="color: rgb(0, 0, 0);"><span style="background-color: transparent;">Winter months can sometimes feel overwhelming, especially if you’re already struggling with depression or anxiety. Taking time for mindfulness, meditation, or simple breathing exercises can help you stay grounded and calm. These practices allow you to focus on the present moment rather than becoming overwhelmed by thoughts about the past or future.</span></span></p>
<p><span style="color: rgb(0, 0, 0);"><span style="background-color: transparent;">Mindfulness can help you cope with stress and anxiety, making it easier to manage negative emotions. Apps like Headspace or Calm offer guided meditations and relaxation techniques that are great for beginners.</span></span></p>
<p><br /></p>
<h3><span style="color: rgb(0, 0, 0);"><span style="background-color: transparent;"><strong>8. Embrace Winter’s Unique Beauty</strong></span></span></h3>
<p><span style="color: rgb(0, 0, 0);"><span style="background-color: transparent;">Lastly, take time to appreciate the beauty of winter. Though the season can be long and challenging, it offers its own unique charm—snowy landscapes, cozy nights in, and the chance to reflect. Engage with the season in a way that feels right for you, whether it’s by enjoying winter sports, observing nature’s transformation, or simply enjoying a hot drink and a good book indoors.</span></span></p>
<p><br /></p>
<p><span style="color: rgb(0, 0, 0);"><span style="background-color: transparent;">Winter doesn’t have to be synonymous with a dip in mood or energy. By taking proactive steps to manage your mental health, you can navigate the season in a way that fosters self-compassion, balance, and well-being. Whether it&apos;s through staying connected with others, getting outside, or practicing mindfulness, remember that the winter blues are a temporary phase, and with the right strategies, you can thrive despite the chill.</span></span></p>
<p><span style="color: rgb(0, 0, 0);"><span style="background-color: transparent;">If the winter blues start to feel overwhelming or are lasting longer than usual, it might be time to reach out for professional support. </span></span></p>
<p><span style="color: rgb(0, 0, 0);"><span style="background-color: transparent;">If you’re struggling with your mental health this winter, it’s important to reach out for help—you&apos;re not alone, and support is available.</span></span></p>
<p><span style="color: rgb(0, 0, 0);"><span style="background-color: transparent;">Stay warm, stay well, and take care of yourself this winter.</span></span></p>]]></content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Surviving the Holidays: Staying Joyful and Sane]]></title><description><![CDATA[The holiday season is a magical time of year. Twinkling lights, festive music, and gatherings of loved ones create an atmosphere of...]]></description><link>https://www.creating-solutions.org/post/surviving-the-holidays-staying-joyful-and-sane</link><guid isPermaLink="false">674df9a5cf5a0840716aacb1</guid><pubDate>Mon, 02 Dec 2024 18:48:26 GMT</pubDate><enclosure url="https://static.wixstatic.com/media/703483_b0119a5971ae45c3b3d1796b78c75f03~mv2.jpg/v1/fit/w_1000,h_1000,al_c,q_80/file.png" length="0" type="image/png"/><dc:creator>Mary Rogers Kirby</dc:creator><content:encoded><![CDATA[<figure><img src="https://static.wixstatic.com/media/703483_b0119a5971ae45c3b3d1796b78c75f03~mv2.jpg/v1/fit/w_1000,h_1000,al_c,q_80/file.png"></figure>
<p>The holiday season is a magical time of year. Twinkling lights, festive music, and gatherings of loved ones create an atmosphere of warmth and celebration. Yet, it’s no secret that this season can also be stressful. Between hosting, shopping, family dynamics, and packed schedules, it’s easy to feel overwhelmed.With a bit of planning and a few mindset shifts, you can navigate the holidays with grace and even enjoy them to the fullest.</p>
<p><br /></p>
<h3>1. <strong>Prioritize What Matters Most</strong></h3>
<p>The holidays often come with an unwritten rule that we have to do <em>everything</em>. But in reality, focusing on what matters most—whether that’s family, traditions, or rest—can help you find joy amidst the chaos. Ask yourself:</p>
<ul>
  <li><p>What memories do I want to create this year?</p></li>
  <li><p>Which activities or events truly align with my values?</p></li>
  <li><p>What can I let go of to make space for what’s meaningful?</p></li>
</ul>
<p>Give yourself permission to say &quot;no&quot; to commitments that don’t bring you joy or serve your well-being.</p>
<p><br /></p>
<h3>2. <strong>Practice Self-Care</strong></h3>
<p>Your physical and mental health is your greatest asset during the holidays. Between late nights and rich meals, it’s easy to neglect your well-being. Make self-care a priority:</p>
<ul>
  <li><p><strong>Sleep:</strong> Aim for 7-8 hours of sleep, even if it means leaving a party early.</p></li>
  <li><p><strong>Eat Mindfully:</strong> Enjoy festive foods, but balance indulgence with nourishment.</p></li>
  <li><p><strong>Move Your Body:</strong> A quick walk or stretch can help manage holiday stress.</p></li>
  <li><p><strong>Take Breaks:</strong> It’s okay to step away for a few minutes of quiet when things get overwhelming.</p></li>
</ul>
<p><br /></p>
<h3>3. <strong>Manage Family Dynamics with Grace</strong></h3>
<p>Holiday gatherings can be joyous, but they can also bring up challenges in family relationships. Prepare yourself with strategies to navigate tricky dynamics:</p>
<ul>
  <li><p><strong>Set Boundaries:</strong> Communicate your needs and limits calmly and assertively.</p></li>
  <li><p><strong>Focus on Gratitude:</strong> Shift your attention to what you appreciate about your loved ones.</p></li>
  <li><p><strong>Let Go of Perfection:</strong> Not every moment will be picture-perfect, and that’s okay.</p></li>
</ul>
<p><br /></p>
<h3>4. <strong>Embrace Imperfection</strong></h3>
<p>The pursuit of a &quot;perfect&quot; holiday can rob you of joy. If things don’t go as planned, take a deep breath and remember that imperfections often create the most cherished memories. The burnt cookies, mismatched wrapping paper, or forgotten gift can become the stuff of laughter and connection.</p>
<p><br /></p>
<h3>5. <strong>Stay Present</strong></h3>
<p>It’s easy to get caught up in the whirlwind of planning and doing. But the true beauty of the holidays lies in the moments we share with those we love. Be intentional about staying present:</p>
<ul>
  <li><p>Put down your phone during meals and conversations.</p></li>
  <li><p>Soak in the little joys, like the sound of laughter or the sparkle of lights.</p></li>
  <li><p>Reflect on the year and the blessings it brought, no matter how small.</p></li>
</ul>
<p><br /></p>
<p>Surviving the holidays doesn’t mean you have to settle for stress and exhaustion. By focusing on what truly matters, simplifying your commitments, and caring for yourself, you can turn this season into one of joy, connection, and <u>meaning.</u><a href="http://meaning.So" target="_blank"> </a><u><a href="http://meaning.So" target="_blank">So</a></u>, put on your coziest sweater, and embrace the holidays in a way that feels right for you. After all, the season is about celebrating love and togetherness—not perfection.</p>
<p>Happy Holidays! </p>]]></content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[How Gratitude can Support Your Mental Health]]></title><description><![CDATA[Gratitude goes beyond a simple “than you” or acts of kindness. Its impact is more far reaching. Cultivating gratitude, even in small...]]></description><link>https://www.creating-solutions.org/post/how-gratitude-can-support-your-mental-health</link><guid isPermaLink="false">6727efbc6308391e76978d2e</guid><pubDate>Sun, 03 Nov 2024 21:51:13 GMT</pubDate><enclosure url="https://static.wixstatic.com/media/7828c72ae30b01463f0009536b0ea837.jpg/v1/fit/w_1000,h_667,al_c,q_80/file.png" length="0" type="image/png"/><dc:creator>Mary Rogers Kirby</dc:creator><content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><br /></p>
<figure><img src="https://static.wixstatic.com/media/7828c72ae30b01463f0009536b0ea837.jpg/v1/fit/w_1000,h_667,al_c,q_80/file.png"></figure>
<p><span style="color: rgb(0, 0, 0);"><span style="background-color: transparent;">Gratitude goes beyond a simple “than you” or acts of kindness. Its impact is more far reaching. Cultivating gratitude, even in small ways, can transform how we see ourselves, interact with others, and handle life’s inevitable challenges.</span></span></p>
<p><span style="color: rgb(0, 0, 0);"><span style="background-color: transparent;">Studies have shown that gratitude affects the brain in significant ways. When we express gratitude, our brain releases dopamine and serotonin, two neurotransmitters responsible for feelings of happiness and contentment. This release can instantly lift our mood, making us feel lighter and more at ease. In fact, regular gratitude practice can even &quot;rewire&quot; the brain, training it to look for and focus on the positives, which can lead to long-term mental health benefits.</span></span></p>
<p><br /></p>
<p><span style="color: rgb(0, 0, 0);"><span style="background-color: transparent;">Neuroscientists have found that gratitude activates the brain’s reward system, particularly in the areas linked to emotional regulation and stress relief. When we practice gratitude regularly, it can help us become more resilient, making it easier to manage stress, reduce symptoms of anxiety and depression, and maintain a more balanced perspective even during challenging times.</span></span></p>
<p><span style="color: rgb(0, 0, 0);"><span style="background-color: transparent;">Here are some specific ways gratitude supports mental health:</span></span></p>
<p><br /></p>
<ul>
  <li><p><strong><span style="color: rgb(0, 0, 0);"><span style="background-color: transparent;">Reduces stress and anxiety</span></span></strong><span style="color: rgb(0, 0, 0);"><span style="background-color: transparent;">: </span></span></p></li>
</ul>
<p><br /></p>
<p><span style="color: rgb(0, 0, 0);"><span style="background-color: transparent;">Focusing on what we are thankful for shifts our attention away from stressors and worries. When we recognize positive aspects of our lives, no matter how small, it helps create a mental buffer against stress. This perspective can calm the mind, reducing anxiety and helping us feel more grounded.</span></span></p>
<p><br /></p>
<ul>
  <li><p><strong><span style="color: rgb(0, 0, 0);"><span style="background-color: transparent;">Boosts mood and happiness</span></span></strong><span style="color: rgb(0, 0, 0);"><span style="background-color: transparent;">:</span></span></p></li>
</ul>
<p><br /></p>
<p><span style="color: rgb(0, 0, 0);"><span style="background-color: transparent;">Gratitude directly contributes to an uplifted mood by enhancing positive emotions and reducing negative ones. Studies have shown that people who regularly practice gratitude report feeling happier, more optimistic, and more satisfied with life. This emotional boost is especially helpful for those struggling with depression, as it gently encourages a shift from ruminating on negative thoughts to noticing moments of joy and connection.</span></span></p>
<p><br /></p>
<ul>
  <li><p><strong><span style="color: rgb(0, 0, 0);"><span style="background-color: transparent;">Enhances resilience</span></span></strong><span style="color: rgb(0, 0, 0);"><span style="background-color: transparent;">:</span></span></p></li>
</ul>
<p><br /></p>
<p><span style="color: rgb(0, 0, 0);"><span style="background-color: transparent;">Life is full of ups and downs, but gratitude helps us approach these challenges with resilience. By focusing on the silver linings, gratitude makes it easier to cope with difficult situations. This doesn’t mean ignoring hardships but rather acknowledging the positives that coexist with them, which strengthens our ability to bounce back and find solutions when faced with setbacks.</span></span></p>
<p><br /></p>
<ul>
  <li><p><strong><span style="color: rgb(0, 0, 0);"><span style="background-color: transparent;">Improves self-esteem and reduces social comparison</span></span></strong><span style="color: rgb(0, 0, 0);"><span style="background-color: transparent;">: </span></span></p></li>
</ul>
<p><br /></p>
<p><span style="color: rgb(0, 0, 0);"><span style="background-color: transparent;">Practicing gratitude for our own achievements and qualities helps foster self-acceptance and self-worth. Grateful people are less likely to engage in social comparisons and feel more secure in their own lives. Rather than feeling envious of what others have, they’re more likely to feel content with what they themselves possess, reducing negative self-judgment and improving overall self-esteem.</span></span></p>
<p><br /></p>
<ul>
  <li><p><strong><span style="color: rgb(0, 0, 0);"><span style="background-color: transparent;">Strengthens relationships:</span></span></strong></p></li>
</ul>
<p><br /></p>
<p><span style="color: rgb(0, 0, 0);"><span style="background-color: transparent;">Expressing gratitude deepens our connections with others by showing appreciation for the people around us. Research has shown that those who regularly express gratitude to partners, friends, or colleagues experience stronger relationships and higher levels of social support. Gratitude fosters empathy, understanding, and a sense of belonging, which can reduce loneliness and improve overall mental health.</span></span></p>
<p><br /></p>
<ul>
  <li><p><strong><span style="color: rgb(0, 0, 0);"><span style="background-color: transparent;">Promotes mindfulness:</span></span></strong></p><p><br /></p></li>
</ul>
<p><span style="color: rgb(0, 0, 0);"><span style="background-color: transparent;">Gratitude shifts our focus from past regrets or future anxieties to the present moment. When we take the time to appreciate the “now,” whether it&apos;s a sunny day or a heartfelt conversation, we experience a form of mindfulness that helps reduce rumination and cultivates a more peaceful state of mind.</span></span></p>
<p><br /></p>
<p><span style="color: rgb(0, 0, 0);"><span style="background-color: transparent;">As gratitude becomes a regular practice, its effects on mental health often become more profound. Over time, individuals who practice gratitude consistently report feeling more at peace with themselves and less focused on life’s negatives. Instead, they find themselves equipped with a toolkit of resilience, optimism, and inner joy. While it does not erase the challenges and difficulties we face, providing a steady foundation to face them with a more balanced, hopeful perspective.</span></span></p>]]></content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Self-Care Tips You Can Do Today]]></title><description><![CDATA[Self-care is often synonymous with indulgent bubble baths, sipping on a warm cup of tea or coffee, or treating ourselves to occasional...]]></description><link>https://www.creating-solutions.org/post/self-care-tips-you-can-do-today</link><guid isPermaLink="false">66fadab12cfab79bcafd36d9</guid><pubDate>Mon, 30 Sep 2024 17:11:04 GMT</pubDate><enclosure url="https://static.wixstatic.com/media/703483_e9b051a2ce6b4eb1a115dc11522b7d9b~mv2.jpg/v1/fit/w_1000,h_1000,al_c,q_80/file.png" length="0" type="image/png"/><dc:creator>Mary Rogers Kirby</dc:creator><content:encoded><![CDATA[<figure><img src="https://static.wixstatic.com/media/703483_e9b051a2ce6b4eb1a115dc11522b7d9b~mv2.jpg/v1/fit/w_1000,h_1000,al_c,q_80/file.png"></figure>
<p><span style="color: #000000;"><span style="background-color: transparent;">Self-care is often synonymous with indulgent bubble baths, sipping on a warm cup of tea or coffee, or treating ourselves to occasional luxuries. Self-care is about consistent practices we can incorporate into our daily lives. Because, who has time for bubble baths every day? In the midst of catering to the needs of others, we often neglect our own well-being. Self-care is far from selfish. Here are five practical self-care ideas you can start implementing right away:</span></span></p>
<p><br /></p>
<ol>
  <li><p><span style="color: #000000;"><span style="background-color: transparent;">Take a break from technology. Put down your phone and turn off the T.V. Resist the urge to endlessly scroll through social media or news feeds. You&apos;d be surprised how much time you can reclaim by disconnecting. Engage in screen-free activities like reading a book or pursuing a hobby. Simply be present in the moment without the distractions of technology.</span></span></p></li>
  <li><p><span style="color: #000000;"><span style="background-color: transparent;">Set boundaries. Don’t be afraid to say no when necessary. Prioritize activities and commitments that replenish your energy and well-being, rather than overextending yourself with unnecessary stressors. Consistently enforce your boundaries, knowing that they may need adjustment or flexibility from time to time.</span></span></p></li>
  <li><p><span style="color: #000000;"><span style="background-color: transparent;">Practice gratitude. Cultivate a daily practice of gratitude by acknowledging at least three things you&apos;re thankful for each day. Shifting your focus to the positives in your life can significantly enhance your overall well-being and perspective.</span></span></p></li>
  <li><p><span style="color: #000000;"><span style="background-color: transparent;">Connect with others. Take a break from work and engage in non-work-related conversations with colleagues. Make time to connect with loved ones, even if it&apos;s just sharing a meal together or reaching out to a friend you haven&apos;t spoken to in a while. Human connection is essential for nurturing our emotional well-being. For more about connection, see my previous post about the loneliness epidemic.</span></span></p></li>
  <li><p><span style="color: #000000;"><span style="background-color: transparent;">Make sleep a priority. Do you really need to watch more tiktok videos or check instagram when you should be sleeping? Create a  routine for bedtime that elicits relaxation.</span></span></p></li>
  <li><p><br /></p></li>
</ol>
<p><span style="color: #000000;"><span style="background-color: transparent;">Start with a few changes and then you can add more as these ideas become more habitual. Make yourself a priority. Nurture yourself so you can show up as your best self.</span></span></p>
<p><span style="color: #000000;"><span style="background-color: transparent;">Do you feel like you need to make more major changes in your life or just don’t know what direction to take? I provide free 15 minute consultations for therapy. Check out my website at </span></span><u><span style="color: #1155cc;"><span style="background-color: transparent;"><a href="http://www.creating-solutions.org" target="_blank">www.creating-solutions.org</a></span></span></u><span style="color: #000000;"><span style="background-color: transparent;">.</span></span></p>
<p><br /></p>
<p><br /></p>
<p><span style="color: #000000;"><span style="background-color: transparent;">This post is solely my opinion and not intended to be a replacement for professional help.</span></span></p>
<p><span style="color: #000000;"><span style="background-color: transparent;">#mentalhealthmatters #mentalhealthhelp #mentalhealththerapy #therapy #selfcare #nurture</span></span></p>]]></content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Striking a Balance]]></title><description><![CDATA[Finding a balance between work and personal life can be a real challenge. The demands of our jobs can leave us feeling drained and...]]></description><link>https://www.creating-solutions.org/post/striking-a-balance</link><guid isPermaLink="false">66d8825bb2c744b3076a5640</guid><pubDate>Wed, 04 Sep 2024 15:55:29 GMT</pubDate><enclosure url="https://static.wixstatic.com/media/703483_101a8ae76de94811b94858857f4efc9e~mv2.jpg/v1/fit/w_1000,h_819,al_c,q_80/file.png" length="0" type="image/png"/><dc:creator>Mary Rogers Kirby</dc:creator><content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><br /></p>
<figure><img src="https://static.wixstatic.com/media/703483_101a8ae76de94811b94858857f4efc9e~mv2.jpg/v1/fit/w_1000,h_819,al_c,q_80/file.png"></figure>
<p><span style="color: #000000;"><span style="background-color: transparent;">Finding a balance between work and personal life can be a real challenge. The demands of our jobs can leave us feeling drained and </span></span><span style="color: #000000;"><span style="background-color: transparent;"><a href="http://overwhelmed.Here" target="_blank">overwhelmed.Here</a></span></span><span style="color: #000000;"><span style="background-color: transparent;"> are some practical tips that can help you reclaim your time and energy.</span></span></p>
<ul>
  <li><h4><strong><span style="color: #000000;"><span style="background-color: transparent;">Give Yourself a Break</span></span></strong></h4></li>
</ul>
<p><span style="color: #000000;"><span style="background-color: transparent;">We’re often our harshest critics, pushing ourselves to meet impossible standards. However, this relentless drive can lead to burnout. It&apos;s crucial to recognize that perfection is unattainable and that it’s okay to take a step back. It’s okay to simply do the best you can.</span></span></p>
<ul>
  <li><h4><strong><span style="color: #000000;"><span style="background-color: transparent;">Take Breaks Throughout the Day</span></span></strong></h4></li>
</ul>
<p><span style="color: #000000;"><span style="background-color: transparent;">We’ve all heard the phrase “work smarter, not harder,” and one of the smartest things you can do is to take regular breaks throughout your workday. Continuous work without rest can decrease productivity and lead to exhaustion. Short, frequent breaks can refresh your mind, improve focus, and prevent burnout. A quick walk, a few minutes of stretching, or even a short meditation session can make a world of difference. By scheduling regular breaks, you’ll find that you’re more productive and less stressed.</span></span></p>
<ul>
  <li><h4><strong><span style="color: #000000;"><span style="background-color: transparent;">Learn to Say No</span></span></strong></h4></li>
</ul>
<p><span style="color: #000000;"><span style="background-color: transparent;">One of the biggest challenges in maintaining a work-life balance is the inability to say no. We often take on too much, whether it’s additional work assignments, social obligations, or favors for friends. While it’s great to be helpful, overcommitting can lead to stress and a lack of personal time. Learning to say no is essential for protecting your well-being. Politely decline tasks or requests that will overburden you and are not your responsibility or in job description. Prioritize what’s most important. Saying no isn’t selfish; it’s a necessary step in managing your time and energy.</span></span></p>
<ul>
  <li><h4><strong><span style="color: #000000;"><span style="background-color: transparent;">Delegate Tasks</span></span></strong></h4></li>
</ul>
<p><span style="color: #000000;"><span style="background-color: transparent;">You don’t have to do everything yourself. At work, identify tasks that others can handle and trust your team to take them on. Ensure that you communicate your expectations clearly. Encourage open communication, allowing them to ask questions or seek clarification as needed.</span></span></p>
<p><br /></p>
<p><span style="color: #000000;"><span style="background-color: transparent;">Part of a work/life balance is what you do with your personal life outside of work. Here are some tips to take care of your time outside of work.</span></span></p>
<ul>
  <li><h4><strong>Set good boundaries</strong></h4></li>
</ul>
<p><span style="color: #000000;"><span style="background-color: transparent;">Establish these boundaries early on. Don’t create an expectation that you are always “on.” it’s easy to feel like you need to be available 24/7. Stop responding to emails or taking phone calls outside of designated work hours. You don’t want to set the precedent that you are always available.Work-related social events can be a great way to build relationships and network, but they can also eat into your personal time if not managed carefully. It’s important to be selective about which social engagements you attend. </span></span></p>
<ul>
  <li><h4><strong>Disconnect from Technology</strong></h4></li>
</ul>
<p><span style="color: #000000;"><span style="background-color: transparent;">In our digital age, it’s easy to get caught up in a constant cycle of checking emails, social media, and messages. To achieve a balanced personal life, it’s important to disconnect from technology regularly. Set aside time each day to unplug and engage in activities that don’t involve screens. This could be reading a book, taking a walk, or spending quality time with loved ones. Disconnecting helps you to be more present in the moment and reduces the mental clutter that technology often brings.</span></span></p>
<ul>
  <li><h4><strong><span style="color: #000000;"><span style="background-color: transparent;">Establish a Routine that Includes &quot;Me Time&quot;</span></span></strong></h4></li>
</ul>
<p><span style="color: #000000;"><span style="background-color: transparent;">Routines are not just for work—they can also help you carve out time for yourself. Schedule regular &quot;me time&quot; into your day, just as you would for any important task. This could be a morning walk, an evening bath, or time set aside for a hobby. By including personal time in your routine, you make sure it becomes a priority rather than an afterthought. Sticking to this routine helps you maintain a sense of balance and ensures that you’re not neglecting your own needs.</span></span></p>
<ul>
  <li><h4><strong><span style="color: #000000;"><span style="background-color: transparent;">Cultivate Social Connections</span></span></strong></h4></li>
</ul>
<p><span style="color: #000000;"><span style="background-color: transparent;">A fulfilling personal life includes strong social connections. Make time to nurture relationships with friends, family, and loved ones. Whether it’s planning regular meetups, chatting over the phone, or organizing a fun activity together, these connections provide emotional support and enhance your sense of belonging. </span></span></p>
<p><span style="color: #000000;"><span style="background-color: transparent;">Achieving a balanced personal life requires intentional effort and a commitment to prioritizing your well-being. By setting boundaries, disconnecting from technology, establishing routines, and nurturing social connections, you can cultivate a more fulfilling and balanced life. Remember, your personal life is just as important as your professional one, and taking steps to enrich it will lead to greater overall happiness and fulfillment.</span></span></p>
<p><br /></p>]]></content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Kicking Off College: Your Guide to Starting and Thriving]]></title><description><![CDATA[Starting college is a big deal! It’s an exciting time full of new experiences, new friends, and a whole lot of independence. But with all...]]></description><link>https://www.creating-solutions.org/post/kicking-off-college-your-guide-to-starting-and-thriving</link><guid isPermaLink="false">66b3bb7e45487db10c2f4477</guid><pubDate>Wed, 07 Aug 2024 18:24:54 GMT</pubDate><enclosure url="https://static.wixstatic.com/media/703483_0d5b9c17989546d0b7fa9aec53db4340~mv2.jpg/v1/fit/w_1000,h_853,al_c,q_80/file.png" length="0" type="image/png"/><dc:creator>Mary Rogers Kirby</dc:creator><content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><br /></p>
<figure><img src="https://static.wixstatic.com/media/703483_0d5b9c17989546d0b7fa9aec53db4340~mv2.jpg/v1/fit/w_1000,h_853,al_c,q_80/file.png"></figure>
<p><span style="color: #000000;"><span style="background-color: transparent;">Starting college is a big deal! It’s an exciting time full of new experiences, new friends, and a whole lot of independence. But with all these changes, it’s totally normal to feel a bit overwhelmed. Here are some tips to make your transition to college life as smooth as possible.</span></span></p>
<p><br /></p>
<h4><span style="color: #000000;"><span style="background-color: transparent;"><strong>1. Roll with the Changes</strong></span></span></h4>
<p><span style="color: #000000;"><span style="background-color: transparent;">College is all about new stuff—new people, new ideas, new places. It’s easy to feel out of your element at first, but try to roll with it. Keep an open mind and be ready to step out of your comfort zone. The more you embrace the changes, the easier it’ll be to settle in and start enjoying all that college has to offer.</span></span></p>
<p><br /></p>
<h4><span style="color: #000000;"><span style="background-color: transparent;"><strong>2. Set Up a Routine ASAP</strong></span></span></h4>
<p><span style="color: #000000;"><span style="background-color: transparent;">One of the biggest differences between high school and college is how you manage your time. With no one telling you when to do what, it’s easy to let things slide. Get ahead of the game by setting up a routine early on. Block out time for classes, studying, meals, and other activities. Having a routine helps you stay on track without burning out.</span></span></p>
<p><br /></p>
<h4><span style="color: #000000;"><span style="background-color: transparent;"><strong>3. Get to Know Your Campus</strong></span></span></h4>
<p><span style="color: #000000;"><span style="background-color: transparent;">Your college campus is going to be your home base for the next few years, so get familiar with it. Take some time to explore—find your classrooms, the library, the gym, and where to grab food. The more you know your way around, the more confident you’ll feel. Plus, it’s nice not to be that person who’s always lost.</span></span></p>
<p><br /></p>
<h4><span style="color: #000000;"><span style="background-color: transparent;"><strong>4. Put Yourself Out There</strong></span></span></h4>
<p><span style="color: #000000;"><span style="background-color: transparent;">Meeting new people can be nerve-wracking, but it’s also one of the best parts of college. Introduce yourself to people in your dorm, your classes, or at events. Join clubs or organizations that catch your eye. The sooner you start building connections, the quicker you’ll feel like you belong. </span></span></p>
<p><br /></p>
<h4><span style="color: #000000;"><span style="background-color: transparent;"><strong>5. Stay on Top of Your Studies</strong></span></span></h4>
<p><span style="color: #000000;"><span style="background-color: transparent;">College classes can be a step up from what you’re used to, so it’s important to stay on top of things from the start. Go to class, participate, and don’t be afraid to ask questions. If you’re struggling, contact your professors during office hours—they’re there to help. Study groups are also a great way to keep up with coursework and make new friends at the same time.</span></span></p>
<p><br /></p>
<h4><span style="color: #000000;"><span style="background-color: transparent;"><strong>6. Watch Your Wallet</strong></span></span></h4>
<p><span style="color: #000000;"><span style="background-color: transparent;">For many students, college is the first time you’re really managing your own money. It can be tempting to splurge, but it’s smart to budget. Keep track of your expenses, look for deals, and find ways to save where you can—like buying used textbooks or cooking instead of eating out all the time. Keeping your finances in check will save you a lot of stress.</span></span></p>
<p><br /></p>
<h4><span style="color: #000000;"><span style="background-color: transparent;"><strong>7. Take Care of Yourself</strong></span></span></h4>
<p><span style="color: #000000;"><span style="background-color: transparent;">With everything going on, it’s easy to let self-care slide, but it’s super important. Make sure you’re getting enough sleep, eating right, and finding time to move your body—whether it’s hitting the gym or just going for a walk. Mental health is just as important as physical health, so don’t hesitate to reach out if you’re feeling overwhelmed. Most campuses have counseling services that are there for you.</span></span></p>
<p><br /></p>
<h4><span style="color: #000000;"><span style="background-color: transparent;"><strong>8. Balance Fun and Responsibility</strong></span></span></h4>
<p><span style="color: #000000;"><span style="background-color: transparent;">College gives you a lot of freedom, which is awesome, but it also comes with responsibility. Finding a balance between having fun and handling your obligations is key. It’s all about making smart choices—enjoy your social life, but don’t forget about your studies, your health, and your future goals. Getting this balance right will help you thrive.</span></span></p>
<p><br /></p>
<h4><span style="color: #000000;"><span style="background-color: transparent;"><strong>9. Stay Connected with Home</strong></span></span></h4>
<p><span style="color: #000000;"><span style="background-color: transparent;">As exciting as college is, staying connected with your family and friends from home is important too. Keep in touch through texts, calls, or video chats. They’re your support system, and talking to them can help when you’re feeling homesick or stressed. Plus, they’ll love hearing from you!</span></span></p>
<p><br /></p>
<h4><span style="color: #000000;"><span style="background-color: transparent;"><strong>10. Be Kind to Yourself</strong></span></span></h4>
<p><span style="color: #000000;"><span style="background-color: transparent;">The transition to college can be a rollercoaster of emotions. It’s normal to feel a mix of excitement, nerves, and everything in between. Give yourself time to adjust and don’t be too hard on yourself if things don’t go perfectly right away. Everyone’s college journey is different, so focus on your own path and trust that you’ll find your way.</span></span></p>
<h3></h3>
<p><span style="color: #000000;"><span style="background-color: transparent;">Transitioning to college is a big step, but it’s also the start of an incredible adventure. By embracing the changes, setting up a routine, and taking care of yourself, you’ll be setting the stage for a successful and enjoyable college experience. Remember, it’s not just about the academics—college is a time to grow, explore, and make memories.</span></span></p>]]></content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Mindful Doodling]]></title><description><![CDATA[Meditation comes in all forms, so there is something for everyone. Mindful doodling is a simple and accessible art form and has emerged...]]></description><link>https://www.creating-solutions.org/post/mindful-doodling</link><guid isPermaLink="false">6682d22bc2fd8fbe360a1b5e</guid><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jul 2024 17:13:38 GMT</pubDate><enclosure url="https://static.wixstatic.com/media/703483_dd14864539fa4568b54b0013e66a403f~mv2.jpg/v1/fit/w_1000,h_1000,al_c,q_80/file.png" length="0" type="image/png"/><dc:creator>Mary Rogers Kirby</dc:creator><content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><br /></p>
<p><br /></p>
<p><br /></p>
<figure><img src="https://static.wixstatic.com/media/703483_dd14864539fa4568b54b0013e66a403f~mv2.jpg/v1/fit/w_1000,h_1000,al_c,q_80/file.png"></figure>
<p><br /></p>
<p><span style="color: #000000;"><span style="background-color: transparent;">Meditation comes in all forms, so there is something for everyone. Mindful doodling is a simple and accessible art form and has emerged as a powerful practice that combines the benefits of mindfulness meditation and creative expression. We all know about the more complex coloring books that can be utilized as meditation, but doodling involves creating spontaneous and unplanned drawings while maintaining a present-moment awareness. It isn’t just scribbling. Mindfulness paired with doodling can lead to a meditative state through predictive and repetitive strokes.</span></span></p>
<p><br /></p>
<p><span style="color: #000000;"><span style="background-color: transparent;">I have had plenty of clients, especially students, who would doodle. I now can see that this was a way they were staying grounded and self-regulating, probably without even realizing it.</span></span></p>
<p><br /></p>
<p><span style="color: #000000;"><span style="background-color: transparent;">Getting started with mindful doodling requires minimal materials. All you need is a blank piece of paper, a pen or pencil, and an open mind. Here are some steps to guide you through the process:</span></span></p>
<p><br /></p>
<ol>
  <li><p><span style="color: #000000;"><span style="background-color: transparent;">Find a quiet space: Choose a calm environment where you can focus without distractions. It could be a designated creative corner in your home, a quiet park, or any place where you feel at ease.</span></span></p></li>
  <li><p><span style="color: #000000;"><span style="background-color: transparent;">Set an intention: Begin by setting an intention for your mindful doodling session. It could be to relax, inspire creativity, or simply enjoy the process of drawing without any expectations.</span></span></p></li>
  <li><p><span style="color: #000000;"><span style="background-color: transparent;">Breathe and center yourself: Take a few deep breaths to anchor yourself in the present moment. Allow your mind to settle, letting go of any thoughts or worries.</span></span></p></li>
  <li><p><span style="color: #000000;"><span style="background-color: transparent;">Start doodling: Begin drawing on the blank paper, allowing your pen or pencil to move freely. Let go of any preconceived ideas and surrender to the flow of the lines and shapes that emerge.</span></span></p></li>
  <li><p><span style="color: #000000;"><span style="background-color: transparent;">Observe without judgment: As you doodle, observe your thoughts and emotions without judgment. Notice any tendencies to label or evaluate your drawings. Remember that the goal is to be fully present and enjoy the act of doodling itself, rather than striving for perfection.</span></span></p></li>
  <li><p><span style="color: #000000;"><span style="background-color: transparent;">Explore different patterns and textures: Experiment with various patterns, shapes, and textures as you continue doodling. Feel free to add colors or shading if it enhances your experience.</span></span></p></li>
  <li><p><span style="color: #000000;"><span style="background-color: transparent;">Embrace the process: Engaging in mindful doodling is not about creating a finished product</span></span></p></li>
</ol>
<p><br /></p>]]></content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[June is Pride Month]]></title><description><![CDATA[The LGBTQ+ community is struggling with mental health issues. According to a 2023 survey from the Trevor Project: 41% of LGBTQ young...]]></description><link>https://www.creating-solutions.org/post/june-is-pride-month</link><guid isPermaLink="false">666094045774552d43f5d015</guid><pubDate>Wed, 05 Jun 2024 16:37:15 GMT</pubDate><enclosure url="https://static.wixstatic.com/media/nsplsh_88dbf971630446759f07c54fffad454d~mv2.jpg/v1/fit/w_1000,h_1000,al_c,q_80/file.png" length="0" type="image/png"/><dc:creator>Mary Rogers Kirby</dc:creator><content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><br /></p>
<figure><img src="https://static.wixstatic.com/media/nsplsh_88dbf971630446759f07c54fffad454d~mv2.jpg/v1/fit/w_1000,h_1000,al_c,q_80/file.png"></figure>
<p><span style="color: #000000;"><span style="background-color: transparent;">The LGBTQ+ community is struggling with mental health issues. According to a 2023 survey from the Trevor Project:</span></span></p>
<p><br /></p>
<ul>
  <li><p><span style="color: #000000;"><span style="background-color: transparent;"><strong>41% of LGBTQ young people seriously considered attempting suicide in the past year</strong></span></span><span style="color: #000000;"><span style="background-color: transparent;">—and young people who are transgender, nonbinary, and/or people of color reported higher rates than their peers.</span></span></p></li>
  <li><p><span style="color: #000000;"><span style="background-color: transparent;"><strong>56% of LGBTQ young people</strong></span></span><span style="color: #000000;"><span style="background-color: transparent;"> who wanted mental health care in the past year </span></span><span style="color: #000000;"><span style="background-color: transparent;"><strong>were not able to get it.</strong></span></span></p></li>
  <li><p><span style="color: #000000;"><span style="background-color: transparent;"><strong>Fewer than 40% of LGBTQ young people</strong></span></span><span style="color: #000000;"><span style="background-color: transparent;"> found their home to be LGBTQ-affirming.</span></span></p></li>
  <li><p><span style="color: #000000;"><span style="background-color: transparent;"><strong>Nearly 1 in 3 LGBTQ young people</strong></span></span><span style="color: #000000;"><span style="background-color: transparent;"> said their </span></span><span style="color: #000000;"><span style="background-color: transparent;"><strong>mental health was poor</strong></span></span><span style="color: #000000;"><span style="background-color: transparent;"> most of the time or always </span></span><span style="color: #000000;"><span style="background-color: transparent;"><strong>due to anti-LGBTQ policies and legislation.</strong></span></span></p></li>
</ul>
<p><br /></p>
<p><span style="color: #000000;"><span style="background-color: transparent;">The Census Bureau survey from 2022 reported:</span></span></p>
<ul>
  <li><p><span style="color: #000000;"><span style="background-color: transparent;">Younger respondents, whether they are LGBT or non-LGBT, struggled more with both anxiety and depression symptoms, </span></span><span style="color: #000000;"><span style="background-color: transparent;"><strong>but younger LGBT respondents struggled the most.</strong></span></span></p></li>
</ul>
<p><br /></p>
<p><span style="color: #000000;"><span style="background-color: transparent;">It’s important for people from the LGBTQ+ community to feel comfortable accessing services and therefore it is on us as clinicians to provide LGBTQ+ affirming care. It is also important to be advocates for this community.</span></span></p>
<p><br /></p>
<p><span style="color: #000000;"><span style="background-color: transparent;">At Creating Solutions, I provide LGBTQ+ affirming care, focusing on anxiety, depression and trauma.</span></span></p>]]></content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[The Loneliness Epidemic]]></title><description><![CDATA[America is experiencing a loneliness epidemic. The U.S. Surgeon Genera released an advisory a year ago on the public health crisis of...]]></description><link>https://www.creating-solutions.org/post/the-loneliness-epidemic</link><guid isPermaLink="false">6633a8b6e5e985820702bc2b</guid><pubDate>Fri, 03 May 2024 15:41:18 GMT</pubDate><enclosure url="https://static.wixstatic.com/media/703483_22864f4b5ef0468c91ba480b7b854f13~mv2.jpg/v1/fit/w_202,h_250,al_c,q_80/file.png" length="0" type="image/png"/><dc:creator>Mary Rogers Kirby</dc:creator><content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><br /></p>
<p><br /></p>
<figure><img src="https://static.wixstatic.com/media/703483_22864f4b5ef0468c91ba480b7b854f13~mv2.jpg/v1/fit/w_202,h_250,al_c,q_80/file.png"></figure>
<p><br /></p>
<p><span style="color: #000000;"><span style="background-color: transparent;">America is experiencing a loneliness epidemic. The U.S. Surgeon Genera released an advisory a year ago on the public health crisis of loneliness and it&apos;s still relevant See the HHS release here: </span></span></p>
<p><br /></p>
<p><a href="https://www.hhs.gov/sites/default/files/surgeon-general-social-connection-advisory.pdf" target="_blank">https://www.hhs.gov/sites/default/files/surgeon-general-social-connection-advisory.pdf</a></p>
<p><br /></p>
<p><span style="color: #000000;"><span style="background-color: transparent;">It says that loneliness and chronic isolation can lead to mental health issues and premature death. While it’s unfortunate the U.S. is grappling with this, I’m glad attention is being placed on this issue.</span></span></p>
<p><br /></p>
<p><span style="color: #000000;"><span style="background-color: transparent;">I have seen this sense of loneliness in clients time and time again, particularly teens and young adults. It is significantly impacting their mental health. While the COVID pandemic certainly played a factor in this issue, it was there before COVID hit. Here are some reasons why:</span></span></p>
<p><br /></p>
<ul>
  <li><p><span style="color: #000000;"><span style="background-color: transparent;">Social media and technology: Social media has led to less and less face to face socialization. Social media by design leads to comparison, leaving users feeling excluded or inadequate and furthering a sense of isolation. Face to face socializing requires some skills that aren’t being practiced as often when socializing virtually. </span></span></p></li>
</ul>
<p><br /></p>
<ul>
  <li><p><span style="color: #000000;"><span style="background-color: transparent;">Performance pressure: Academic and performance pressure can feel overwhelming. I often see adolescents who feel the pressure to make top grades and perform at a high level in extracurriculars. The pressure often becomes of their own making as opposed to explicit messages. They often don’t recognize the more implicit ones that over time, create this internal monologue that they must succeed. Due to the pressure, they spend much more time focused on academics or extracurriculars, saving little room for more casual, beneficial social interactions. </span></span></p></li>
</ul>
<p><br /></p>
<ul>
  <li><p><span style="color: #000000;"><span style="background-color: transparent;">Lack of supportive relationships: I have noticed that my adolescent clients sometimes struggle to develop supportive friendships. Their loneliness can get compounded with unhealthy friendships as they retreat even more due to these negative experiences. Friendships during adolescence are challenging.</span></span></p></li>
</ul>
<p><br /></p>
<p><span style="color: #000000;"><span style="background-color: transparent;">This list is not exhaustive and there are many other factors that have led to this epidemic.</span></span></p>
<p><br /></p>
<p><span style="color: #000000;"><span style="background-color: transparent;">If you or someone you care about is experiencing loneliness or struggling socially, I am here to help. Just head over to my website: </span></span><u><a href="http://www.creating-solutions.org" target="_blank"><span style="color: #1155cc;"><span style="background-color: transparent;">www.creating-solutions.org</span></span></a></u></p>
<p><br /></p>
<p><span style="color: #000000;"><span style="background-color: transparent;">The opinions expressed in this post are solely my own and are not a substitute for professional therapy.</span></span></p>
<p><br /></p>
<p><a href="https://www.instagram.com/explore/tags/mentalwellness/" target="_blank"><span style="color: #000000;"><span style="background-color: transparent;">#mentalwellness</span></span></a><a href="https://www.instagram.com/explore/tags/mentalhealthsupport/" target="_blank"><span style="color: #000000;"><span style="background-color: transparent;"> #mentalhealthsupport</span></span></a><a href="https://www.instagram.com/explore/tags/therapist/" target="_blank"><span style="color: #000000;"><span style="background-color: transparent;"> #therapist</span></span></a><a href="https://www.instagram.com/explore/tags/memories/" target="_blank"><span style="color: #000000;"><span style="background-color: transparent;"> </span></span></a><a href="https://www.instagram.com/explore/tags/onlinetherapy/" target="_blank"><span style="color: #000000;"><span style="background-color: transparent;">#onlinetherapy</span></span></a><a href="https://www.instagram.com/explore/tags/virtualtherapy/" target="_blank"><span style="color: #000000;"><span style="background-color: transparent;"> #virtualtherapy</span></span></a><a href="https://www.instagram.com/explore/tags/bewell/" target="_blank"><span style="color: #000000;"><span style="background-color: transparent;"> #bewell</span></span></a><a href="https://www.instagram.com/explore/tags/wellnesssupport/" target="_blank"><span style="color: #000000;"><span style="background-color: transparent;"> </span></span></a></p>
<p><a href="https://www.instagram.com/explore/tags/wellnesssupport/" target="_blank"><span style="color: #000000;"><span style="background-color: transparent;">#wellnesssupport</span></span></a><a href="https://www.instagram.com/explore/tags/findatherapist/" target="_blank"><span style="color: #000000;"><span style="background-color: transparent;"> #findatherapist</span></span></a><a href="https://www.instagram.com/explore/tags/mentalhealthawareness/" target="_blank"><span style="color: #000000;"><span style="background-color: transparent;"> #mentalhealthawareness</span></span></a><a href="https://www.instagram.com/explore/tags/mentalhealthhelp/" target="_blank"><span style="color: #000000;"><span style="background-color: transparent;"> #mentalhealthhelp </span></span></a><a href="https://www.instagram.com/explore/tags/mentalhealthcounseling/" target="_blank"><span style="color: #000000;"><span style="background-color: transparent;">#mentalhealthcounseling</span></span></a><a href="https://www.instagram.com/explore/tags/mentalhealthmatters/" target="_blank"><span style="color: #000000;"><span style="background-color: transparent;"> #mentalhealthmatters</span></span></a><span style="color: #000000;"><span style="background-color: transparent;"> #mentalhealthchallenge #therapistsofinsta </span></span><a href="https://www.instagram.com/explore/tags/stress/" target="_blank"><span style="color: #000000;"><span style="background-color: transparent;">#stress</span></span></a><a href="https://www.instagram.com/explore/tags/panic/" target="_blank"><span style="color: #000000;"><span style="background-color: transparent;"> #panic</span></span></a><a href="https://www.instagram.com/explore/tags/stressedout/" target="_blank"><span style="color: #000000;"><span style="background-color: transparent;"> #stress</span></span></a><a href="https://www.instagram.com/explore/tags/stressrelief/" target="_blank"><span style="color: #000000;"><span style="background-color: transparent;"> #stressrelief</span></span></a><a href="https://www.instagram.com/explore/tags/coping/" target="_blank"><span style="color: #000000;"><span style="background-color: transparent;"> #coping</span></span></a><a href="https://www.instagram.com/explore/tags/copingskills/" target="_blank"><span style="color: #000000;"><span style="background-color: transparent;"> #copingskills</span></span></a><a href="https://www.instagram.com/explore/tags/nyctherapist/" target="_blank"><span style="color: #000000;"><span style="background-color: transparent;"> #vatherapist</span></span></a><a href="https://www.instagram.com/explore/tags/cbttherapist/" target="_blank"><span style="color: #000000;"><span style="background-color: transparent;"> </span></span></a><span style="color: #000000;"><span style="background-color: transparent;">#therapistsofIG #therapistthoughts #therapistsofva #growth #healing #care #allarewelcome #loneliness</span></span></p>
<p><br /></p>
<p><br /></p>]]></content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Pillars of Good Mental Health]]></title><description><![CDATA[When it comes to nurturing our mental health, we often focus on psychological strategies or therapies. However, we must not overlook the...]]></description><link>https://www.creating-solutions.org/post/pillars-of-good-mental-health</link><guid isPermaLink="false">662183a4fc879605230e3b98</guid><pubDate>Thu, 18 Apr 2024 20:37:53 GMT</pubDate><enclosure url="https://static.wixstatic.com/media/703483_53515bc490ad413faea98ce7418d8e0e~mv2.png/v1/fit/w_1000,h_720,al_c,q_80/file.png" length="0" type="image/png"/><dc:creator>Mary Rogers Kirby</dc:creator><content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><br /></p>
<p><br /></p>
<figure><img src="https://static.wixstatic.com/media/703483_44275d5905fa4be0a44f9f10c244be53~mv2.png/v1/fit/w_1000,h_466,al_c,q_80/file.png"></figure>
<p><br /></p>
<p><span style="color: rgb(0, 0, 0);"><span style="background-color: transparent;">When it comes to nurturing our mental health, we often focus on psychological strategies or therapies. However, we must not overlook the significant impact that sleep, physical activity, and good nutrition have on our overall well-being. This triad forms a crucial foundation for maintaining good mental health.</span></span></p>
<p><br /></p>
<ul>
  <li><p><span style="color: rgb(0, 0, 0);"><span style="background-color: transparent;">Sleep: Sleep is a fundamental pillar of mental health. It allows our bodies and minds to rest, recharge, and repair. Sufficient sleep is essential for cognitive functioning, emotional regulation, and memory consolidation. When we lack sleep, we become more susceptible to stress, anxiety, and depression.</span></span></p></li>
</ul>
<p><br /></p>
<p><span style="color: rgb(0, 0, 0);"><span style="background-color: transparent;">Quality sleep promotes mental clarity, concentration, and creativity. It enhances                      our ability to handle daily stressors and boosts overall resilience. Establishing good                sleep hygiene can help with a restful night&apos;s sleep.</span></span></p>
<p><br /></p>
<ul>
  <li><p><span style="color: rgb(0, 0, 0);"><span style="background-color: transparent;">Physical Activity: Physical activity is not only beneficial for our physical health but also plays a pivotal role in maintaining good mental well-being. Exercise releases endorphins, the &quot;feel-good&quot; hormones, which elevate mood, reduce stress, and improve self-esteem.</span></span></p></li>
</ul>
<p><br /></p>
<p><span style="color: rgb(0, 0, 0);"><span style="background-color: transparent;">Physical activity promotes better sleep patterns and boosts brain health by increasing blood flow and oxygenation. It can enhance cognitive function, memory, and concentration. Incorporating exercise into our daily routine, whether through walking, jogging, yoga, or other activities we enjoy, helps manage stress, anxiety, and depression while fostering a positive mindset.</span></span></p>
<p><br /></p>
<ul>
  <li><p><span style="color: rgb(0, 0, 0);"><span style="background-color: transparent;">Good Nutrition: The food we consume significantly impacts our mental health. A balanced diet rich in essential nutrients is essential for optimal brain function and emotional well-being. Nutrient deficiencies can lead to mood swings, fatigue, and cognitive impairments.</span></span></p></li>
</ul>
<p><br /></p>
<p><span style="color: rgb(0, 0, 0);"><span style="background-color: transparent;">Eating a diet that includes fruits, vegetables, whole grains, lean proteins, and healthy fats provides the necessary nutrients for brain health. Omega-3 fatty acids, found in fatty fish and walnuts, have been linked to improved mood and reduced symptoms of depression. Avoiding excessive sugar, processed foods, and alcohol can help stabilize mood and prevent energy crashes.</span></span></p>
<p><br /></p>
<p><span style="color: rgb(0, 0, 0);"><span style="background-color: transparent;">By incorporating these three elements into our lives, we create a strong foundation for mental health, enabling us to navigate life&apos;s challenges with greater resilience, improved mood, and enhanced overall well-being. Prioritize sleep, physical activity, and good nutrition as key pillars of our mental well-being.</span></span></p>
<p><br /></p>
<p>Want to do more for your mental health? Book your consultation today!</p>
<p><br /></p>
<p><br /></p>
<p><br /></p>
<p><span style="color: rgb(0, 0, 0);"><span style="background-color: transparent;">This is not to be used as medical advice. Please consult your doctor.</span></span></p>
<p><br /></p>
<p><span style="color: rgb(0, 0, 0);"><span style="background-color: transparent;">#nutrition #goodsleep #exercise #mentalhealthhelp #mentalhealthcounseling #therapy #findatherapist</span></span></p>]]></content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Impact of Trauma on the Brain]]></title><description><![CDATA[The impact of trauma on the brain is complex but here are some important things to know: The amygdala is a part of the brain that scans...]]></description><link>https://www.creating-solutions.org/post/impact-of-trauma-on-the-brain</link><guid isPermaLink="false">6621830bf9554c888bf7807e</guid><pubDate>Thu, 18 Apr 2024 20:31:42 GMT</pubDate><enclosure url="https://static.wixstatic.com/media/11062b_248aae69aef44ef7a320af986c51c346~mv2.jpg/v1/fit/w_1000,h_1000,al_c,q_80/file.png" length="0" type="image/png"/><dc:creator>Mary Rogers Kirby</dc:creator><content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><br /></p>
<p><br /></p>
<figure><img src="https://static.wixstatic.com/media/11062b_248aae69aef44ef7a320af986c51c346~mv2.jpg/v1/fit/w_1000,h_1000,al_c,q_80/file.png"></figure>
<p><br /></p>
<p><span style="color: rgb(0, 0, 0);"><span style="background-color: transparent;">The impact of trauma on the brain is complex but here are some important things to know:</span></span></p>
<p><br /></p>
<p><span style="color: rgb(0, 0, 0);"><span style="background-color: transparent;">The amygdala is a part of the brain that scans for threat. It’s like our brain’s fire alarm. The traumatized brain has an overactive amygdala. The fire alarm keeps going off even if there is no smoke or fire.</span></span></p>
<p><br /></p>
<p><span style="color: rgb(0, 0, 0);"><span style="background-color: transparent;">One of the roles of the hippocampus is memory formation. Due to trauma, the hippocampus’ functioning is impacted, leading to difficulties in forming and consolidating memories. This can result in fragmented or distorted recollections of the traumatic event.</span></span></p>
<p><br /></p>
<p><span style="color: rgb(0, 0, 0);"><span style="background-color: transparent;">Our prefrontal cortex is responsible for executive functioning skills, like weighing decisions, planning, and problem-solving. When something is assessed as dangerous or a threat, our prefrontal cortex isn’t working as much. Trauma disrupts the prefrontal cortex, leading to difficulties in regulating emotions, making rational decisions, and controlling impulsive behavior.</span></span></p>
<p><br /></p>
<p><span style="color: rgb(0, 0, 0);"><span style="background-color: transparent;">The good news in all of this is that our brains are resilient and can be rewired and changed to restore better functioning in these areas of the brain. Interested in how?</span></span></p>
<p><span style="color: rgb(0, 0, 0);"><span style="background-color: transparent;">Schedule a free consultation.</span></span></p>
<p><br /></p>
<p>This information is not a replacement for professional help.</p>
<p><br /></p>
<p><span style="color: rgb(0, 0, 0);"><span style="background-color: transparent;">#traumatreatment #healingtrauma #findatherapist #mentalhealthhelp #mentalhealthcounseling #mentalhealth</span></span></p>]]></content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Having a hard time finding a therapist?]]></title><description><![CDATA[You’re looking for a therapist and google “find a therapist near me.” Maybe you’re being more specific with your needs like anxiety,...]]></description><link>https://www.creating-solutions.org/post/having-a-hard-time-finding-a-therapist</link><guid isPermaLink="false">662181a2bcf26abeecfa1432</guid><pubDate>Thu, 18 Apr 2024 20:27:26 GMT</pubDate><enclosure url="https://static.wixstatic.com/media/11062b_94cea79840544aacac22d5dfed5ef8e8~mv2.jpeg/v1/fit/w_1000,h_1000,al_c,q_80/file.png" length="0" type="image/png"/><dc:creator>Mary Rogers Kirby</dc:creator><content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><br /></p>
<p><br /></p>
<figure><img src="https://static.wixstatic.com/media/11062b_94cea79840544aacac22d5dfed5ef8e8~mv2.jpeg/v1/fit/w_1000,h_1000,al_c,q_80/file.png"></figure>
<p><br /></p>
<p><span style="color: rgb(0, 0, 0);"><span style="background-color: transparent;">You’re looking for a therapist and google “find a therapist near me.” Maybe you’re being more specific with your needs like anxiety, depression or trauma in your search. What seems like a plethora of therapists turns out to be a frustrating search. There are several factors that contribute to this experience. </span></span></p>
<p><br /></p>
<ul>
  <li><p><em><span style="color: rgb(0, 0, 0);"><span style="background-color: transparent;">Availability: Sometimes professionals don’t update where they are listed that they are no longer taking new clients. The Consolidated Appropriations Act requires insurance companies to reach out to providers to update their directory entry every 90 days, otherwise, the entry is suppressed. But, it is up to the clinicians to provide updates to their availability in other listings like </span></span></em><a href="http://therapist.com" target="_blank"><em><span style="color: rgb(0, 0, 0);"><span style="background-color: transparent;">therapist.com</span></span></em></a><em><span style="color: rgb(0, 0, 0);"><span style="background-color: transparent;">, Psychology Today or their own website.</span></span></em></p></li>
  <li><p><em><span style="color: rgb(0, 0, 0);"><span style="background-color: transparent;">Demand: Especially since the pandemic, therapists are in higher demand. Some areas like rural areas just don’t have enough therapists to meet the needs of their community. Overall, we know there are not enough therapists to help the number of people seeking therapy.</span></span></em></p></li>
  <li><p><em><span style="color: rgb(0, 0, 0);"><span style="background-color: transparent;">Populations: Some populations have even less therapists serving them. Finding a child or adolescent client can be more challenging. If the search is for a very specific problem, like an eating disorder, there are less therapists who have the training and background to treat that person.</span></span></em></p></li>
  <li><p><em><span style="color: rgb(0, 0, 0);"><span style="background-color: transparent;">Cost: Ideally, people would like to utilize their insurance to help cover the cost of therapy. Less and less therapists are taking insurance. This can be cost prohibitive for many people.</span></span></em></p></li>
</ul>
<p><br /></p>
<p><span style="color: rgb(0, 0, 0);"><span style="background-color: transparent;">This list is not exhaustive. If you are seeking a therapist, I am available and I do take insurance. Check out my website to see if I might be a good fit for your needs.</span></span></p>
<p><br /></p>
<p><span style="color: rgb(0, 0, 0);"><span style="background-color: transparent;">Be well!</span></span></p>
<p><br /></p>
<p><span style="color: rgb(0, 0, 0);"><span style="background-color: transparent;">These opinions are solely my own.</span></span></p>
<p><br /></p>
<p><span style="color: rgb(0, 0, 0);"><span style="background-color: transparent;">#findatherapist #mentalhealthsupport #fightthestigma #mentalhealth #therapist #mentalhealthsupport #mentalhealthcounts #anxiety #depression</span></span></p>]]></content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Building Resilience in Times of Stress]]></title><description><![CDATA[Resilience is the ability to bounce back from adversity, trauma, or stress. It is not a trait that people either have or do not have, but...]]></description><link>https://www.creating-solutions.org/post/building-resilience-in-times-of-stress</link><guid isPermaLink="false">6607d60cce87136565575de2</guid><pubDate>Sat, 30 Mar 2024 09:07:49 GMT</pubDate><enclosure url="https://static.wixstatic.com/media/703483_8e6459e21028446b98390817c6a49986~mv2.jpg/v1/fit/w_1000,h_1000,al_c,q_80/file.png" length="0" type="image/png"/><dc:creator>Mary Rogers Kirby</dc:creator><content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><br /></p>
<p><br /></p>
<figure><img src="https://static.wixstatic.com/media/703483_8e6459e21028446b98390817c6a49986~mv2.jpg/v1/fit/w_1000,h_1000,al_c,q_80/file.png"></figure>
<p><br /></p>
<p>Resilience is the ability to bounce back from adversity, trauma, or stress. It is not a trait that people either have or do not have, but rather a skill that can be developed over time. Building resilience can help you cope with life&apos;s challenges more effectively and recover from setbacks more quickly.</p>
<p><br /></p>
<p>There are several ways to build resilience:</p>
<p><br /></p>
<ul>
  <li><p><strong>Maintain a Positive Outlook</strong>: Try to see challenges as opportunities for growth and learning.</p></li>
  <li><p><strong>Develop Healthy Coping Strategies</strong>: Find healthy ways to cope with stress, such as exercise, meditation, or talking to a therapist.</p></li>
  <li><p><strong>Build Strong Relationships</strong>: Cultivate supportive relationships with friends, family, and community members.</p></li>
  <li><p><strong>Take Care of Yourself</strong>: Get enough sleep, eat a healthy diet, and make time for activities you enjoy.</p></li>
</ul>
<p><br /></p>
<p>By building resilience, you can become more adept at handling life&apos;s ups and downs and emerge stronger and more capable of facing future challenges.</p>
<p><br /></p>
<p>#stress #stressreduction #resiliency #mentalhealth #mentalhealthsupport #wellness </p>]]></content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Understanding Anxiety: Causes and Coping Strategies]]></title><description><![CDATA[Anxiety is a common mental health condition that affects millions of people worldwide. It is characterized by feelings of worry, fear,...]]></description><link>https://www.creating-solutions.org/post/understanding-anxiety-causes-and-coping-strategies</link><guid isPermaLink="false">6607d55c692f768303ccd58a</guid><pubDate>Sat, 30 Mar 2024 09:04:58 GMT</pubDate><enclosure url="https://static.wixstatic.com/media/703483_dd5cccd567d54fa18c0ca3de3f65aa23~mv2.jpg/v1/fit/w_1000,h_683,al_c,q_80/file.png" length="0" type="image/png"/><dc:creator>Mary Rogers Kirby</dc:creator><content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><br /></p>
<figure><img src="https://static.wixstatic.com/media/703483_dd5cccd567d54fa18c0ca3de3f65aa23~mv2.jpg/v1/fit/w_1000,h_683,al_c,q_80/file.png"></figure>
<p><br /></p>
<p>Anxiety is a common mental health condition that affects millions of people worldwide. It is characterized by feelings of worry, fear, and apprehension that are often accompanied by physical symptoms such as sweating, trembling, and rapid heartbeat. While some level of anxiety is normal in certain situations, excessive or persistent anxiety can interfere with daily life and may require professional treatment.</p>
<p><br /></p>
<p>The causes of anxiety are complex and can vary from person to person. Some common factors that may contribute to anxiety include genetics, brain chemistry, personality, and life experiences. Additionally, certain medical conditions and medications can also contribute to feelings of anxiety.</p>
<p><br /></p>
<p>Fortunately, there are several effective coping strategies for managing anxiety:</p>
<p><br /></p>
<ul>
  <li><p><strong>Mindfulness and Meditation</strong>: Practicing mindfulness and meditation can help calm the mind and reduce anxiety symptoms.</p></li>
  <li><p><strong>Physical Activity</strong>: Regular exercise can help reduce anxiety and improve overall mood.</p></li>
  <li><p><strong>Healthy Lifestyle Choices</strong>: Eating a balanced diet, getting enough sleep, and avoiding alcohol and caffeine can help manage anxiety.</p></li>
  <li><p><strong>Cognitive Behavioral Therapy (CBT)</strong>: CBT is a type of therapy that helps individuals identify and change negative thought patterns and behaviors that contribute to anxiety.</p></li>
</ul>
<p><br /></p>
<p>If you or someone you know is struggling with anxiety, it&apos;s important to seek help from a mental health professional. With the right support and treatment, it is possible to manage anxiety and lead a fulfilling life.</p>
<p><br /></p>
<p>Want to manage your anxiety better? Book a free consultation!</p>
<p><br /></p>
<p>#anxiety #mentalhealth #mentalhealthsupport #findatherapist #therapist #onlinetherapy</p>]]></content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[The Importance of Self-Care]]></title><description><![CDATA[Self-care is often misunderstood as selfish or indulgent, but in reality, it is an essential aspect of maintaining our mental, emotional,...]]></description><link>https://www.creating-solutions.org/post/the-importance-of-self-care</link><guid isPermaLink="false">6607d4383a7dd5ddb2691e46</guid><pubDate>Sat, 30 Mar 2024 09:01:13 GMT</pubDate><enclosure url="https://static.wixstatic.com/media/703483_1644784c9079444c857842df59f0049f~mv2.jpg/v1/fit/w_1000,h_1000,al_c,q_80/file.png" length="0" type="image/png"/><dc:creator>Mary Rogers Kirby</dc:creator><content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><br /></p>
<p><br /></p>
<figure><img src="https://static.wixstatic.com/media/703483_1644784c9079444c857842df59f0049f~mv2.jpg/v1/fit/w_1000,h_1000,al_c,q_80/file.png"></figure>
<p><br /></p>
<p>Self-care is often misunderstood as selfish or indulgent, but in reality, it is an essential aspect of maintaining our mental, emotional, and physical well-being. Self-care encompasses a wide range of activities, from simple acts of kindness towards ourselves to more structured practices that nurture our overall health.</p>
<p><br /></p>
<p>In today&apos;s fast-paced world, it&apos;s easy to neglect self-care in favor of keeping up with responsibilities and commitments. However, prioritizing self-care is crucial for preventing burnout and maintaining a healthy work-life balance. By taking the time to care for ourselves, we are better equipped to handle stress, improve our mood, and enhance our overall quality of life.</p>
<p><br /></p>
<p>Here are some simple self-care practices you can incorporate into your daily routine:</p>
<p><br /></p>
<ul>
  <li><p><strong>Physical Self-Care</strong>: Get enough sleep, eat nutritious meals, and engage in regular exercise.</p></li>
  <li><p><strong>Emotional Self-Care</strong>: Practice self-compassion, journaling, or seek support from loved ones.</p></li>
  <li><p><strong>Social Self-Care</strong>: Connect with friends and family, join a community group, or volunteer.</p></li>
  <li><p><strong>Spiritual Self-Care</strong>: Engage in activities that nourish your soul, such as meditation, prayer, or spending time in nature.</p></li>
</ul>
<p><br /></p>
<p>Remember, self-care is not a luxury but a necessity. By making self-care a priority, you can improve your overall well-being and lead a more fulfilling life.</p>
<p><br /></p>
<p>Want to do more for your self-care? Book a free consultation!</p>
<p>#selfcare #mentalhealth #mentalhealthsupport #findatherapist #therapist #onlinetherapy</p>]]></content:encoded></item></channel></rss>